Guide to the Pittsburgh Council, American Youth Hostel Records, 1955-2002 AIS.2004.20
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Council, American Youth Hostel Records
1955-2002
ULS Archives & Special Collections
American Youth Hostels, inc. Pittsburgh Council
AIS.2004.20
20 Linear Feet (16 boxes)
The Pittsburgh Council was chartered and incorporated in 1955 as a chapter of American Youth Hostels. These records show the routine operations of the council and the wide range of outdoor activities in which it participated, as well as the building of the Pittsburgh International Hostel. Documents date from the creation of the council's charter in 1955 through 2002, shortly before the hostel closed.
History
Youth Hostels began in Germany in 1910 as a way to provide basic lodging facilities for traveling students. The idea soon spread internationally, with the first hostel in the United States opening in Northfield, Massachusetts. The concept proved ideal to young men and women looking to explore their own countries as well as others. Affordable travel, coupled with the bountiful outdoor activities that hostelling presented, opened up new opportunities for travel to large segments of the population, especially for younger people.
In 1948, members of the community first explored the options of starting a Pittsburgh chapter of the American Youth Hostels (AYH). This vision became reality in 1955 as the Pittsburgh Council was chartered and incorporated. Throughout its nearly fifty year history the Pittsburgh Council is perhaps best associated with the multitude of activities and events in which it was involved. Among the first of these was the establishment and maintenance of the Baker Trail, which originally ran from Aspinwall to the Cook State Forest. When development caused the abandonment of the Aspinwall to Freeport section, the trail was extended north to the Allegheny National Forest. The Pittsburgh Council also launched similar efforts at the Rachel Carson Trail system, a setting that remained a focal point of Council hiking activity for decades. Hiking trips were coordinated with local hostels, including Erie, Morgantown, and Ohiopyle. The Council offered a myriad of other outdoor activities including canoeing, kayaking, rafting, climbing, caving and bicycling. Large bicycle tours were also organized and sponsored by the Council. These included the Mon Valley Century ride, the Sabre ride near the Settlers Cabin Park, and the Great Ride, which was a joint effort with Pittsburgh CitiParks.
The Pittsburgh Council hit a high point in the mid and late 1990s, culminating with the opening of the Pittsburgh International Hostel in the neighborhood of Allentown in June 1997. Following the World Trade Center bombing of September 11, 2001, the number of foreign travelers making their way into the United States diminished drastically. Since foreign travelers were the main patrons of the hostel, by the fall of 2003, the hostel was unable to remain in operation and was forced to close its doors. By the spring of 2004 the council leadership felt that with no hostels, an activities program long eclipsed by other competing organizations and a decline in volunteers and memberships, it was time to call an end to the Pittsburgh Council. The Activity Headquarters, located in Mellon Park, was returned to the Pittsburgh Department of Parks and Recreation and the equipment was sold or donated to other organizations.
Scope and Content Notes
These records show the routine operations of the council and a wide range of activities in which it participated, including the building of the Pittsburgh International Hostel. Documents date from the creation of the council's charter in 1955 through 2002, shortly before the hostel closed, with most of them dating from the late 1960s through 2000.
Arrangement
More detailed scope notes are found after each series title. Many subjects and activities are represented across multiple files and series. Researchers should search the collection widely. The records are divided into three series:
Series I. Administrative Files
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Activities
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of by Grant Ervin, the last president of the Council, in September 2004.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Council, American Youth Hostels Records, Inc. 1955-2002, AIS.2004.20, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Associations; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Youth hostels -- United States; Youth hostels -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; American Youth Hostels, inc. Pittsburgh Council
- Administrative Files, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series consists primarily of administrative files that relate to the organizational functions and daily operations of the council. These include financial statements, billing information, and supply inventories. Minutes are interspersed throughout the collection and come from the Pittsburgh Council Board of Directors and the Activities Board (by the late 1980s, these two boards were merged), Regional Meetings, and National Meetings proceeding from American Youth Hostel conferences. There are also a number of membership rolls and statistics detailing the group's goals and objectives during several years. Records from affiliated hostels in Erie, Ohiopyle, Morgantown, Jennerstown, and elsewhere are also housed among this series. Other documents that figure prominently are leadership development packets, chartering information, non-profit by-laws, convention guides, architectural plans, and additional miscellaneous items. The series is arranged chronologically.
  - American Youth Hostel (AYH) Permanent Resource File, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes/Board Resolutions, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Regional Director's Report, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AYH Service, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AYH Trail Design, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Facts, Figures, Minutes, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Affiliates: Questions and Answers, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Insurance Information, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AYH Picnic, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Request for Use: Parks, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - AYH National Directives, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AYH and Outside Organizations, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Board Meeting Minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nursing Care Plans, Minutes, Drawings, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Appalachian Trail, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - AYH Convention Guide, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Membership Information, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National Directives, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hostel Development, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Public Relations, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Leadership Manuals, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Board Minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Balance Sheet, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - National Board Meeting, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - AYH National Board Directives, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Recharter Applications, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Financial Statements, 1964-1983 (Box 2, Folder 01-02)
  - Annual Reports, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Council President, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 04-05)
  - Meeting Minutes, January 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Greater Boston Council, Misc. Information, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Member Mailings, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Charter Renewal, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Quarterly Report, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Materials, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Eastern Regional, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Council Meeting Minutes, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Financial Statements, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pittsburgh Council/By-laws, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Membership Card Information, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Volunteer Readership, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Business Plan Reference Planner, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Accounting Information, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Office Checking to File, 1974-1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Misc. Financial Information, 1974-1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Election Information, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - AYH Pittsburgh Council Meeting Minutes, 1983-1994 (Box 3, Folder 01-21)
  - Otter Creek Guide, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Northern George Washington Forest, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Cranberry Backcountry, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Dolly Sods, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Monongahela National Forest and Vicinity, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Canoeing Guide, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Baker Trail, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Old Stone House, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 01-03)
  - Annual Council Meeting, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 05-06)
  - Retreat and Goals, 1988-1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Annual Council Meeting, Finance and Minutes, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 08-09)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Council Meeting Minutes, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1994-2002 (Box 4, Folder 13-23)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1979-1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Lease Agreement, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Eastern Regional Council By-Laws, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - AYH Annual Report, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Eastern Regional Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Franchise Information: Pittsburgh Council, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Fall Eastern Regional Meeting Minutes, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 07-13)
  - AYH Master Report CAN DO Program, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Misc. Zoning and Renovation Information, 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Eastern Regional Spring Meeting Minutes, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Pittsburgh Council, Misc. Publication Information, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Eastern Region Fall Meeting Minutes, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Real Estate Tax Information, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Minutes, General Information, 1990-1993 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Eastern Regional Meeting Minutes, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - AYH Directors and Officers Agreements, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Audit Information, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Ohiopyle Evaluation Forms, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - CAN DO Reports, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Council Accounting Manual, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 27-30)
  - AYH Auditing Information, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Hostelling International Budget Forecast, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Information, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 33-35)
  - Pittsburgh Council Agenda, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Fiscal and Budget Charts, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 39-41)
  - AYH Retreat Planning, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - AYH Quick Notes, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 45-54)
  - First Quarter Financial Reports, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 56-59)
  - Misc. Pittsburgh Council General, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - AYH Goals, 1985-1992 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - AYH Hostel Operation Information, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Hostel Development, Home Hostels, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Pittsburgh Hostel Inspection Forms, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Lawrenceville Development Information, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Hostel Re-charter Information, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Experience Report Forms, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 07-08)
  - Ohiopyle Miscellaneous, 1996-2001 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Ohiopyle Charter and General Information (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Ohiopyle Hostel Reports, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - Ohiopyle Monthly Reports, 2000-2002 (Box 6, Folder 13-35)
  - President's Files, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Wilkinsburg Hostel Information, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous Hostel Information, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - VRC Replacement Information, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Hostel Development Information, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Energy Efficiency Information, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Crop and Farming Exercise (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Information (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Hostel Songlist Information (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Lake City Re-charter Information (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - AYH National Council Meeting, Hostel Franchising Discussion, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 01-02)
  - AYH Annual Results Report, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - AYH National Council Meeting Information, 1984-1987 (Box 7, Folder 04-06)
  - Hostelling International (HI) National Council Meeting Information, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - AYH National Council Meeting Information, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 08-09)
  - HI Strategic Plan, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - AYH National Council Meeting Information, 1997-1999 (Box 7, Folder 11-13)
  - AYH Hostel Criteria and Philosophy, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - PGH Chapter Council Goals, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Pittsburgh Council Annual Report, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Regent Square School, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Firehouse (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Job Training Retention (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Lake Erie Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Fombell Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Jennerstown Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Schellsburg Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Mars Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Pittsburgh Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Morgantown Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Ohiopyle Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Ruralvalley Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Gettysburg Hostel Development (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - By-Laws and Charter Information, 1955-1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Introduction on History and By-Laws, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Board Minutes and Procedure, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Hostel Site Study, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Pittsburgh Council, AYH By-Laws, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - AYH Hostel Operations Manual, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - AYH National Council Meeting, 41st Annual, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - AYH Resource and Background Material, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - Council Meetings, 44th Annual Convention, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Pittsburgh Council Miscellaneous, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Legislation Copies, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Council Meetings, 45th Annual Convention, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Establishment and Operation, 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Eastern Regional Council, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - AYH Publication and Reports, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Membership Card Information, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - National Membership Committee, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - AYH Personal Directory, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - AYH Pittsburgh Informational Package, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - AYH Pittsburgh Council Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - AYH Government and Regulation, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - United States Hostel Location Map Finder, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Old Stone House Information, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - National Council Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous Pittsburgh Council Activities, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Director Reports, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Rechartering Information, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Strategic Plan: Green Draft, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Organization Information, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Background Material to AYH Presidents, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 34-35)
  - Goals and Objectives for Pittsburgh Council, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - New York International Hostel Bankruptcy Filings, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - CAN DO Needs Assessment, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Melcroft Hostel, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 02-03)
  - Camp Silver/ Chestnut Ridge Camp (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Jennerstown Mars Hotel (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Hostel Applications (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Hostel Operations Manual (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Hostel Chartering and Surveys (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Pittsburgh Jurisdiction, 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Campus Living: Waters and Schellsburg (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Point Park College Hostel (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Camp Sherwin/Rural Valley 1987 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Charleroi Hostel (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Hostel Developments (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Charters, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Extended Trips, 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - By-Laws (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - National Finance (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Financial Statements (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Executive Directors (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - National Board (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - AYH Miscellany (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Case Statement (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Contributions and Requests (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Accounting Manual for AYH Councils (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Trip and Rental Guide (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Leadership Development Guides (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Franchise Operations (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Membership Rolls (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - AYH Annual Reports, 1967-1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Meeting, San Francisco, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Charter Information, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Eastern Regional Meeting Minutes, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Western Regional Meeting Minutes, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - AYH Midwest Regional Meeting Minutes, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - AYH Board Meeting Minutes, New York City, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Health and Safety, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Tax Exemption and Forms, 1976-1985 (Box 10, Folder 09-10)
  - Pittsburgh Council Rechartering Information, 1979-1982 (Box 10, Folder 11-13)
  - Leadership Development, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Board of Director Resolution, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - AYH Fundraising, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Budget Request, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Allentown Planning, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Allentown Financial, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - AYH Financial Reports, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Limited Partnership, 1994-1995 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Financial and Legal Charts, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Architectural Meeting Minutes, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Grant Conditions, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Budget Information, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Regional Asset District, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Urban Redevelopment, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Budget Information, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Fiscal Year Overnight Statistics, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 29-30)
  - Travel Center Reports, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Pittsburgh Council, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1982-1985 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - City Lease, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Goals Committee, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - History Notes, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Eastern Regional, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - AYH Annual Meeting, 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Balance Sheet, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Baker Trail Guide, 1987-1988 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Headquarter Renovation, 1988-1990 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Finance, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Fiscal Year, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - AYH Miscellaneous, 1990-1998 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - AYH Financial and Budget Reports, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - AYH Financing and Accounting, 1991-1999 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Fiscal Year Publication and Reports, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Office Inventory, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Ohiopyle Weekly Reports, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Audit Report, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Rachel Carson Trail, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - AYH Tax Information, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Hostelling International Weekly Reports, 1997-1998 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Hostel Construction, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Tax Returns: Working Copy, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - AYH Miscellaneous, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Annual Council Meeting, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Fiscal Year, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - AYH Budget Information, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Annual Meeting Handouts, undated (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - AYH CAN DO Program Flyers, undated (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Recipes, undated (Box 11, Folder 33-35)
  - Activities Board, undated (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Trip Reports, 1970-1972 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Board Minutes and Proceedings, 1979-1985 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Fiscal Year Accounting, 1982-1987 (Box 12, Folder 03-04)
  - By-Law Accounting, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Hostel Operations, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Hostel Development, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Case Studies for Special Events, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Member Listing, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Hostel Recharter Inspection, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Morgantown Chestnut Ridge, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 11-12)
  - Board Meeting Minutes/Activities, 1985-1987 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Budget Information, 1987-1988 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Recharter, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Activities Board Minutes, 1988-1990 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Pittsburgh Hostel Development and Survey, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Minutes/Information, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Board Meeting Planning, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Charter Procedure, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Board Meeting, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Annual Meeting, 1987-1990 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Council Agreements, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Misc. Hostel Development, 1994-1995 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - AYH National Reports, 1994-1995 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - National Board Proceedings, undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Topographical Maps, undated (Box 12, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, II.
  This series consists of correspondence among presidents of the Pittsburgh Council and other high ranking board members. Although there is correspondence found throughout the collection, this series is generally more focused on leadership posts and often pertains to projects that were given a special relevance, such as the design and construction of the Allentown building and the maintenance of the Baker Trail. By comparison, much of the correspondence found outside of this series is more likely to pertain to the more routine aspects of the organization.
  - AYH President's Letter File, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Summary Reports and Correspondence, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Council President's Correspondence Files, 1972-1975 (Box 13, Folder 03-04)
  - Misc. Correspondence, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 05-06)
  - Board Correspondence, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - AYH Correspondence, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Board Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Organization, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Board Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 11-12)
  - National Board Correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Council Relations Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Board Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 15-18)
  - Audit Letters and Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Board Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Start-Up Correspondence, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - CAN DO Correspondence, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Allentown Architectural Correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Department of Health and Human Service Correspondences, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Board Correspondence, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Baker Trail Correspondence, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 26)